Jacques Quen MD Papers Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
Jacques Quen MD Papers
1961 - 1989
This collection contains the papers of Jacques Quen, who was a historian of psychiatry and active with Cheiron, the International Society for the History of the Behavioral and Social Sciences. The collection has no series and needs to be reprocessed.
.84 linear feet (2 boxes)
Quen, Jacques M., 1928-
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
1985.0001
Gift of Jacques Quen, 1985.
There are no access restrictions on this material.
Dr. Jacques M. Quen was born October 23, 1928 in New York City. He completed his undergraduate studies at Bethany College in West Virginia, his Masters of Science degree from Brown University, and his M.D. at Yale University in 1954. He attended the William Alanson White Institute and received certification as a psychoanalyst in 1973. He became associated with Cornell University Medical College in 1961 and after 1978 continued as a Clinical Professor of Psychiatry.
Quen’s specialty was the history of psychiatry, including Anglo-American history and legal psychiatry. Quen was a member of numerous professional societies including the International Society for the History of the Behavioral and Social Sciences (Cheiron), for which he served on the Structure Committee in the 1970’s. Other memberships included the American Academy of Psychiatry and the Law, the American Academy of Psychoanalysis, and the American Psychiatric Association.
Quen, Jacques M., 1928-; Rosenkrantz, Barbara Gutmann; Brittain, Robert P.; Parssinen, Terry M.; CHEIRON, International Society for the History of the Behavioral and Social Sciences; Psychiatry--History
The collection consists primarily of Quen’s curriculum vitae and correspondence on the history of the behavioral sciences. The dates of the collection are 1961-1989, with the bulk of the materials from the 1970’s. The primary individuals he corresponded with outside of the society to which he belonged were Robert P. Brittain of Scotland, Terry M. Parssinen of Temple University in Philadelphia, and Barbara G. Rosenkrantz of Harvard University. In addition to correspondence with Dr. Quen, the material concerning these three individuals consists of manuscripts of papers and grant proposals from 1967-1980. Mesmerism is the subject of Parssinen’s papers.
Most of the collection pertains to Dr. Quen’s association with Cheiron, the International Society for the History of the Behavioral and Social Sciences. Cheiron was formed in October 1968 at New York University and consisted of persons from various scholarly disciplines interested in the history of their respective fields. Cheiron was formed to promote international, multidisciplinary cooperation for scholarly activity and research in the history of the behavioral and social sciences. The organization’s aims are (a) to provide a broad perspective on the history of contemporary scientific activities capable of counterbalancing the narrowness of specialists’ views (b) to broaden scientific perspectives through close cooperation with scholars in other countries, and (c) to strengthen and increase the professionalization of scholarly research in the history of the behavioral and social sciences. Annual meetings are held in different locations in this country and in Canada. The journal of Cheiron is the Journal of the History of the Behavioral Sciences. The Structure Committee was formed in 1973 with the charge of reviewing the operations of the Cheiron Society and suggesting some minimal structure and basic operating practices. Dr. Quen was a member of this committee in the 1970’s.
Records of Cheiron date from 1971-1981. The material relating to the Structure Committee consists of correspondence pertaining to several committees that the Structure Committee suggested should be formed. Other material pertaining to Cheiron is comprised of programs for annual meetings, handouts, minutes, membership lists, newsletters and correspondence. There are also manuscripts and related correspondence by George Kren, Robert I. Watson Jr., Steve Heims, and David Stang. Additional records pertaining to the Cheiron Society may be found in the Cheiron Society Records in the Oskar Diethelm Library. The collection has no series and needs to be reprocessed.
- No series
  - Curriculum vitae, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Robert P. Brittain, 1967 - 1968 (Box 1)
  - Terry M. Parssinen, 1974 - 1980 (Box 1)
  - Terry M. Parssinen, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Barbara G. Rosenkrantz, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Barbara G. Rosenkrantz, 1975 - 1977 (Box 1)
  - Barbara G. Rosenkrantz. Draft for symposium, “The Method in Madness: Asylum Records as a Resource for the History of Medicine”, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Barbara G. Rosenkrantz. Papers with Maris A. Vinovskis: “Institutional Commitment and Custody in Ante-Bellum America: The Role of the Family, the Community, and the State in Providing Care for the Insane in Massachusetts” and “The Invisible Lunatics: Old Age and Insanity in Mid-Nineteenth Massachusetts”, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Clifford B. Farr, Denis Leigh, 1961 - 1967 (Box 1)
  - Cheiron. Structure Committee, 1976 - 1981 (Box 2)
  - Cheiron. Structure Committee, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Cheiron. Structure Committee, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Cheiron. Structure Committee, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Cheiron. Programs, minutes, membership list, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Cheiron. Programs, minutes, membership list, 1971 - 1972 (Box 2)
  - Cheiron. Program, handouts for annual meeting, related material, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Cheiron. Manuscripts by George Kren and Robert I. Watson, Sr., 1974 (Box 2)
  - Cheiron. Manuscripts and correspondence of Steve Heims and David Stang, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Cheiron. Manuscript and correspondence of Steve Heims, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Cheiron. Program, newsletter, correspondence, 1974 - 1975 (Box 2)
  - Cheiron. Program, newsletter, correspondence, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Cheiron. Correspondence, newsletter, 1977 - 1978 (Box 2)